Ugo Landini

Manager & Software Craftsman

via Centuripe 11
00179 Rome, Italy
T+39 346 3350669
ugo.landini@gmail.com
https://ugol.io

Objective

To drive business growth by leveraging cutting-edge technology, consultative sales, and strategic customer engagement in dynamic and challenging environments.

Summary

With over 25 years of experience in software development and IT, I specialize in helping businesses unlock value through Data Streaming, Data Management, and Application Integration. As a Senior Manager at Confluent, I guide enterprises in adopting real-time streaming solutions that enhance efficiency, innovation, and revenue growth. My expertise extends beyond technology to business strategy, customer success, and solution consulting, enabling me to bridge the gap between technical solutions and business outcomes.

Professional Experience

Throughout my career, I have played key roles in pre-sales, post-sales, and consultative engagements, helping customers implement high-impact solutions. I have a strong track record of influencing stakeholders, identifying business needs, and translating them into technology strategies that drive revenue and competitive advantage. My experience spans solution architecture, enterprise adoption strategy, and executive-level advisory, ensuring that technical solutions align with business goals.

Teaching and Communication

As an experienced speaker and educator, I have a proven ability to convey complex technical concepts to diverse audiences, from students to developers to C-level executives. I have led high-impact presentations, conducted strategic workshops, and contributed to sales enablement initiatives. My ability to articulate value propositions has made me a key contributor in pre-sales engagements, customer advocacy, and thought leadership initiatives.

Community Engagement

I have played an active role in shaping the IT industry through leadership in developer communities and large-scale events. As the former president of JUG Roma and CTO of Codemotion, I have built influential networks of different people at different levels. My presence at international conferences, including Red Hat Summit, Javapolis and Data in Motion has reinforced my reputation as a trusted advisor in the field.

Open Source Contributions

A passionate advocate for Open Source, I have contributed to key projects that have influenced the industry, including JR, HACEP, Apache Camel, and JGroups RAFT. My entrepreneurial mindset has also led to successful software products, such as my Pomodoro app for Mac, which gained recognitions from Apple.

via Centuripe 11 00179 Rome, Italy **T** +39 346 3350669 ugo.landini@gmail.com https://ugol.io

Experience:

Senior Manager @ Confluent

2023-now

 SE Manager for Italy/Iberia. Working within the customer success team to help our clients attain maximum value from data streaming.

JR founder/lead architect

2023-now

- JR is the lead open source synthetic data generation tool
- https://jrnd.io/
- https://github.com/jrnd-io/jr

Staff Solutions Engineer @ Confluent

2019-2022

Everything about Kafka and the Distributed Data streaming world.

HACEP founder/lead architect

2016-2018

- HACEP is an highly available and scalable version of Drools CEP. It's the official Red Hat reference architecture for an Enterprise CEP
- https://access.redhat.com/articles/2542881
- http://redhat-italy.github.io/hacep/

Principal Solution Architect @ Red Hat

2012-2019

- Solution Architect, specialised in everything related to middleware.
- · Camel committer (camel-couchbase), JGroups RAFT committer

Lead Architect @ VMWare

2012

VFabric Architect, specialised in RabbitMQ and Gemfire projects

Founder @ YMobe

2012 - 2014

Utility and Game Developing for iOS (Pomodoro app and other casual games)

CTO Office @ Poste Italiane

2008 - 2012

- Head of ESB/Internet applications
- Some public slides: http://www.slideshare.net/ugolandini/25-tiers

Founder @ Codemotion

2006 - 2015

• Founder and CTO of Codemotion (ex Javaday) http://www.codemotion.it/en

CTO @ Sourcesense/Pronetics

2006 - 2008

 Responsible for the overall technical strategies and handling directly a team of 25 presales/postsales people

Founder @ JUG Roma

2005 - 2012

· President and founder of JUG Roma

Senior Architect @ Sun Microsystems

2003 - 2006

- Architected and designed an ESB for Italian eGovernment, which became a local Italian Sun product.
- Worked as a consultant/mentor/coach on EAI projects for top Sun customers (INPS, Acea, NCR, Telecom, Regione Toscana among the others)

I authorize the collection and processing of my personal data (according to the italian 675/96 law and similar ones)

via Centuripe 11 00179 Rome, Italy **T** +39 346 3350669 ugo.landini@gmail.com https://ugol.io

Team leader @ Sun Microsystems

2000 - 2003

- Managed Enterprise Java Instructors (30 people) in Italy for Sun Educational Services
- Mentored Sun Professional Services Java Architects on Design and Methodological issues

CTO @ EuropeanArtisans.com (RM/NY)

1999 - 2000

- · Designed the architecture for EuropeanArtisans.com, an US startup
- Led a 10 people team in Rome, experimenting eXtreme Programming practices

Team leader @ CGIL Lombardia/CCOO Catalunya (MI)

1998 - 1999

- Designed the Spiderwork framework to help the development of a full Object Oriented n-tier Java/Corba application
- Led a 4 people team, won a prize at Softech 2000 for Software Development Best Practice

Team leader @ OIS Italia

1997 - 1998

- Led a 6 people team for Analysis and Design of a Distributed Software
- Approached the emerging world of Middleware and EAI (Fortè)

Teacher @ PRAEL Sistemi

1996 - 1997

Taught a wide range of courseware, from Office Automation to OOAD ones

Owner @ Shark snc

1994 - 1996

Founded Shark snc, a software factory targeting small business

Entrepreneur @ Honeywell bull

1989 - 1990

 Created my first commercial software to manage Automobil Club Italia (ACI) subagencies, later sold to Honeywell Bull

Public Speeches and Prizes

Big Data Week	Synthetic data generation	2024
Codemotion	Lesson learned from developing JR	2024
Data in Motion	Keynote and tech track lead	2023/4
Geek talk	Interview	2022
Confluent	KSQL and Stream webinar	2021
Confluent	Kafka webinar	2020
Red Hat Summit	JDG & Instant Payment	2018
Red Hat Summit	HACEP lab	2017
Open Source Day	MSA & Openshift	2016
Open Source Day	Fuse Fabric Techlab	2014
Open Source Day	JDG Techlab	2013
Codemotion	Modern Cloud Integration with Fabric	2013
Better Software, WhyMCA	Mobile Programming in LUA	2011
Javaday IV	2.5 tiers architecture	2010
Javapolis, Javaday II	Clustering a real word app with Terracot	ta 2007
Javaday II	Treasure troves of open source	2007
Javaday I	Java Memory Model & Concurrency	2006
Sun Java Conference	Object Oriented Principles	2002/3/4
Consorzio Nettuno	TV Java course (RAI), still aired	2001
UML Day	UML and method(ologie)s	2001

I authorize the collection and processing of my personal data (according to the italian 675/96 law and similar ones)

via Centuripe 11
00179 Rome, Italy
T+39 346 3350669
ugo.landini@gmail.com
https://ugol.io

Softech 2000	Software Development Best Practice	2000
Papers		
https://bit.ly/4gEaAaH https://bit.ly/3DoVh7p Java Journal http://www.mokabyte.it http://www.programmazione.it	JR tutorial part I Infoq JGroups RAFT "Idiomatica" series Fragile Base Class articles & book reviews	2023 2015 2006 2004 2003
Università di Milano	Thesis tutor on "Distributed Programming"	1999

Open Source & Public software

JR Synthetic data generation https://jrnd.io/

HACEP Highly Available CEP http://redhat-italy.github.io/hacep/

Github Personal page https://github.com/ugol

Education and training

Infomedia

Math (uncompleted) Università La Sapienza

Computer Science G.Vallauri

Management Crucial conversations (Red Hat), Associate Man-

ager Program (Red Hat), Manager Program and

Advanced Manager Program (Confluent)

Computer Programming magazine n.97

1999

Sales MEDDPICC sales course (Red Hat)

Professional certifications and Memberships

- Mensa High IQ Society (top 1%)
- · JUG Roma president
- Sun certified Enterprise Architect, Sun certified Java Programmer, JBoss certified specialist, Kafka developer and administration, many others

For more detailed information about my work and contributions, please visit my LinkedIn profile: http://it.linkedin.com/in/ugolandini.